MICHAEL W. KEARNEY, PH.D.

NLP/AI SCIENTIST

mike.wayne.kearney@gmail.com

(816) 447-8650



PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Internationally recognized expert in Data Science, Natural Language, and Artificial Intelligence with over seven years of professional experience, strong theoretical and quantitative backgrounds, and a knack for finding and implementing innovative solutions to complex problems.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

AI SCIENTIST

Aware (client)

Michael Kearney AI Consulting LLC

2023

- Delivered recommendations on use and development of generative AI and large language models
- Described strengths and limitations in data sources and models and estimated project timelines
- Drafted plans to implement/monitor human-in-the-loop AI labeling and offer multi-tier API access

SENIOR AI SCIENTIST

BI Labs

Aware

2022-2023

- Proposed and built information quality model to supercharge summarization and generative AI
- Curated external dataset of half a billion recent, diverse, and heuristically labeled social messages
- Created internal packaging for data visualization and sampling, aggregating, and uploading to S3
- Refactored large language models in PyTorch, implemented best practices, and enabled GPUs
- Converted and parameterized model training workflows from Airflow to Sagemaker Pipelines

SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST

BI Language

Aware

2021-2022

- Owned, improved, and expanded (to non-English) featured NLP models—sentiment & toxic speech
- Automated model reports on inputs, parameters, and metrics (precision, recall, f1, accuracy)
- Mentored junior team members and often contributed tutorials and other documentation
- Delivered public- and client-facing thematic analysis of workplace collaboration messages
- Used SQL and Athena to efficiently query customer data in DynamoDB, Athena, and Redshift
- Frequently worked with datalakes, Apache Arrow columnar format, and unstructured JSON data
- Created labeling rule books, documented edge cases, and trained third party annotators

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

Data Science & Journalism

Univ of Missour

2017-2021

- Developed and taught courses on social media data, networks, machine learning, and statistics
- Mentored dozens of data science and journalism capstones and chaired two doctoral dissertations
- Developed and reviewed open-source data science tools, including popular bot detection software
- Served on various school and university committees related to data, education, and diversity

DATA CONSULTANT

Research Methods Center

Univ of Kansas

2016-2017

- Delivered feedback on interdisciplinary research projects across university system
- Led data science working groups on python, machine learning, and natural language processing
- Contributed to project automating personalized analytics for students in a large school district

INSTRUCTOR

Communication

Univ of Kansas

2012-2016

- Created rtweet, a massively popular R package for collecting and analyzing Twitter data
- Instructor of record for quantitative methods, public speaking, leadership, and persuasion
- · Updated and refined course materials for core quantitative research methods course

TOOLS

LANGUAGES
AWS RESOURCES
WEB DATA COLLECTION
DEV-OPS
DEEP LEARNING
MACHINE LEARNING
NATURAL LANGUAGE
DATA SCIENCE
DATA VIZUALIZATION
REPORTING

Python | R | SQL | Git | Docker | Bash | JavaScript S3 | Sagemaker | ECR | Athena | Redshift | DynamoDB REST/Stream APIs | requests | BS4 | HTTR | Rvest Azure | Jira | GitHub | Gitlab | Confluence | Trello PyTorch | TensorFlow | HuggingFace | Keras Scikit-learn | XGBoost | FastText | Tidymodels Spacy | HuggingFace | NLTK | RegEx | Scikit-learn Polars | Pandas | Numpy | Tidyverse | Data.table Ggplot2 | Ggvis | Plotly | Matplotlib | D3 JupyterNB | Markdown | Knitr | Quarto | LaTeX

SKILLS

THEORY
RESEARCH METHODS
ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE
SUPERVISED LEARNING
UNSUPERVISED LEARNING
LEADERSHIP

Communication | Media | Interpersonal | Opinion/Topic Mining
Experiments | Survey | Annotation | Algorithmic Labeling | Sampling
LLMs | Transformers | Human in the Loop | Reinforcement
Linear Models | Multilevel | Time Series | ANOVA | Structural Equation
Topic Modeling | Network Analysis | PCA | Factor Analysis | Similarity
Project Management | Team Supervisor | Committee Member & Chair

EDUCATION

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (Ph.D. with Honors)	University of Kansas	Lawrence, KS	2017
Communication & Behavioral Sciences Methodology	1		
MASTER OF ARTS (M.A. with Honors)	University of Kansas	Lawrence, KS	2014
Communication Studies			
BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (B.S.)	Missouri State University	Springfield, MO	2012
Socio-Political Communication			

PUBLICATIONS (SELECTED)

PEER-REVIEWED ARTICLES

- Comparative approaches to misinformation, International Journal of Communication, 2021
- Exploring gender differences on Twitter with NLP, Journal of Language and Social Psychology, 2021
- Collecting and analyzing Twitter data, Journal of Open-Source Software, 2019
- Analyzing change in network polarization, New Media Society, 2019
- Two tests of social displacement through social media use, Information, Communication, & Society, 2018
- Interpersonal goals and political uses of Facebook, Communication Research Reports, 2017

POPULAR PRESS ARTICLES

- March Madness office talk on par with Vegas odds, PR Newswire, 2023
- Doubts cast over Elon Musk's Twitter bot claims, BBC News, 2022
- Using data science to uncover mystery author of Times' Op-ed, Reynolds Journalism Institute, 2018
- Trusting News project report, Trusting News, 2017

OPEN-SOURCE SOFTWARE

- tweetbotornot2: Detecting Twitter bots, 100,000 downloads / 27 citations, 2019
- textfeatures: Extracts features from text, 43,000 downloads / 4 citations, 2017
- rtweet: Collecting Twitter data, 1,100,000 downloads / 491 citations, 2016